<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Tops on Cédric Scherer</title>
    <link>/top/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Tops on Cédric Scherer</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    
	<atom:link href="/top/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/top/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/top/about/</guid>
      <description>Click here for the pdf of my resume.
About Me I am a computational ecologist by training and a data visualization designer by heart. I use statistical and simulation models to answer questions related to the movement ecology of animals and the dynamics of populations, communities and diseases in space and time. To visualize my results and all types of data I use mostly R and the package {ggplot2} from the {tidyverse} which I also use for all kinds of data preparation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/top/dataviz/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/top/dataviz/</guid>
      <description>A collection of data visualizations I&amp;rsquo;ve produced for scientific publications and fun using the {ggplot2}(https://ggplot2.tidyverse.org/) package in the programming language R. All visualizations are the result of the code without any post-processing. Click on an image to enlarge it. 
 Contributions to #TidyTuesday Contributions to #MakeoverMonday Contributions to the #SWDchallenge &amp;ldquo;Evolution of a ggplot&amp;rdquo; blog series   Contributions to #TidyTuesday #TidyTuesday is a weekly data project aimed at the R ecosystem and the {tidyverse} package bundle to wrangle, explore and visualize the data set that is provided by the R4DS Online Learning Community.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/top/links/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/top/links/</guid>
      <description>Content  Rstats  {tidyverse} {ggplot2} Spatial Data  DataViz  Colors Chart Types Mapping  Interesting Personal Blogs  Rstats  &amp;ldquo;Cookbook for R&amp;rdquo; — free online book by Winston Chang &amp;ldquo;Technical Foundations of Informatics&amp;rdquo; — free online book by Michael Freeman &amp;amp; Joel Ross &amp;ldquo;Efficient R Programming&amp;rdquo; — free online book by Colin Gillespie &amp;amp; Robin Lovelace &amp;ldquo;YaRrr! The Pirate&amp;rsquo;s Guide to R&amp;rdquo; — free online book by Nathaniel Phillips R Graph Gallery Five Simple Tipps to Improve Your R Code  {tidyverse}  &amp;ldquo;R for Data Science&amp;rdquo; — free online book by Hadley Wickham &amp;amp; Garrett Grolemund  {ggplot2}  Source code of the book &amp;ldquo;Fundamentals of Data Visualization&amp;rdquo; Top 50 ggplot visualizations Gallery of ggplot2 extensions Extending ggplot2  Spatial Data  &amp;ldquo;Geocomputation with R&amp;rdquo; — free online book by Robin Lovelace, Jakub Nowosad &amp;amp; Jannes Muenchow  DataViz  &amp;ldquo;Data Visualization&amp;rdquo; — free online book by Kieran Healy</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/top/projects/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/top/projects/</guid>
      <description>Project Overview  BioMove NLMR (Neutral Landscape Models in R) Multidimensionality of Stability AFT (Animal Functional Type Approach) #TidyTuesday  BioMove The DFG funded Research Training Group &amp;lsquo;Integrating Biodiversity Research with Movement Ecology in dynamic agricultural landscapes (BioMove)&amp;rsquo; aims to:
 link innovative individual research projects that overcome the apparent gap between movement ecology and biodiversity research, employing a joint conceptual framework;
 strategically combine empirical, experimental and modelling approaches based in one common study area (AgroScapeLab-Quillow, Brandenburg, Germany) of sufficient size to address questions of varying spatial scales;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/top/pubs/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/top/pubs/</guid>
      <description>Peer-Reviewed Publications | Conference Contributions | R packages
You can also find me on Google Scholar and ResearchGate.
My ORCID ID is 0000-0003-0465-2543.
Peer-Reviewed Publications  C. Scherer, V. Radchuk, M. Franz, H.-H. Thulke, M. Lange, V. Grimm &amp;amp; S. Kramer-Schadt (accepted) Moving infections: Individual movement decisions drive disease persistence in spatially structured landscapes. Oikos.
 C. Scherer, V. Radchuk, C. Staubach, S. Müller, N. Blaum, H.-H. Thulke &amp;amp; S.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>