<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Tops on Cédric Scherer</title>
    <link>https://cedricscherer.com/top/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Tops on Cédric Scherer</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://cedricscherer.com/top/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://cedricscherer.com/top/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cedricscherer.com/top/about/</guid>
      <description>About Me li:not(:last-child) {margin-bottom: 3px;}I am a graduated computational ecologist by training and an independent data visualization designer/expert by heart with an extensive hypothesis-driven research experience and strong skills in data wrangling, statistical analysis, model development, and data visualization. I have created visualizations across all disciplines, purposes, and styles and regularly teach data visualization principles as well as basic and advanced ggplot2 techniques.
Data Visualization I have been working as an independent data visualization specialist since the beginning of 2020.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://cedricscherer.com/top/challenges/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cedricscherer.com/top/challenges/</guid>
      <description>Overview of Data Visualization Challenges Content  #TidyTuesday #30DayMapChallenge #30DayChartChallenge SWDchallenge #MakeoverMonday RStudio Table Contest BES MoveMap Competition CorrelAid X Challenge  #TidyTuesday The R4DS (&amp;ldquo;R for Data Science&amp;rdquo;) online learning community founded by Jesse Maegan is a great opportunity to train skills related to data wrangling and visualization and forms a network of mentors and learners. One of the first projects born out of this collaboration is #TidyTuesday, a weekly social data project founded by Thomas Mock that focusses on understanding how to summarize and arrange data to make meaningful charts with {ggplot2}, {tidyr}, {dplyr} and other tools in the tidyverse ecosystem.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://cedricscherer.com/top/conduct/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cedricscherer.com/top/conduct/</guid>
      <description>Code of Conduct I take responsibility for my own words and all the content created by myself. I am committed to the “Civility Enforced” standard: I will not post unacceptable content, and I will delete any references or comments that contain it.
I define unacceptable content as anything included or linked to that:
is being used to abuse, harass, stalk, or threaten othersis libelous, knowingly false, ad-hominem, or misrepresents another personinfringes upon a copyright or trademarkviolates an obligation of confidentialityviolates the privacy of othersI define and determine what is “unacceptable content” on a case-by-case basis, and my definitions are not limited to this list.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://cedricscherer.com/top/dataviz/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cedricscherer.com/top/dataviz/</guid>
      <description>A selection of data visualizations I have produced for personal projects and as challenge contributions using the {ggplot2} package in the programming language R. All visualizations are the result of the code without any post-processing.
 #TidyTuesday Contributions #30DayMapChallenge Contributions #MakeoverMonday Contributions #SWDchallenge Contributions RStudio Table Contest   You need a visualization? Let&amp;rsquo;s get in touch! Contributions to #TidyTuesday #TidyTuesday is a weekly data project aimed at the R ecosystem and the {tidyverse} package bundle to wrangle, explore and visualize the data set that is provided by the R4DS Online Learning Community.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://cedricscherer.com/top/impressum/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cedricscherer.com/top/impressum/</guid>
      <description>Impressum Angaben gemäß § 5 TMG C&amp;eacute;dric Scherer
Birkenstra&amp;szlig;e 18
10559 Berlin
Kontakt Telefon: +49 (0) 176 708 789 84
E-Mail: info@data-vizard.de
Verantwortlich für den Inhalt nach § 55 Abs. 2 RStV C&amp;eacute;dric Scherer
Birkenstra&amp;szlig;e 18
10559 Berlin
EU-Streitschlichtung Die Europ&amp;auml;ische Kommission stellt eine Plattform zur Online-Streitbeilegung (OS) bereit: https://ec.europa.eu/consumers/odr. Unsere E-Mail-Adresse finden Sie oben im Impressum.
Verbraucher­streit­beilegung/Universal­schlichtungs­stelle Wir sind nicht bereit oder verpflichtet, an Streitbeilegungsverfahren vor einer Verbraucherschlichtungsstelle teilzunehmen.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://cedricscherer.com/top/links/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cedricscherer.com/top/links/</guid>
      <description>Content  Data Visualization Rstats Personal Blogs  DataViz Open-Access Books  “Data Visualization” by Kieran Healy “Hands-On Data Visualization” by Jack Dougherty &amp;amp; Ilya Ilyankou “Fundamentals of Data Visualization” by Claus Wilke  Readings &amp;amp; Learnings  “Nightingale” — journal by the Data Visualization Society “Our World in Data” — data on the world’s largest problems “Multiple Views: Visualization Research Explained” — data visualization blog on Medium Graphics Principles Explorable Explanations  Color Choice  Viz Palette — colors in action (plus colorblind check) Color Space — color palette generator Chroma.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://cedricscherer.com/top/portfolio/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cedricscherer.com/top/portfolio/</guid>
      <description>Content  Peer-Reviewed Publications Invited Talks Conference Presentations R Packages Media Appearances  Peer-Reviewed Publications You can also find me on Google Scholar and ResearchGate.
My ORCID ID is 0000-0003-0465-2543.
Accepted   L. Marescot, M. Franz, S. Benhaiem, H. Hofer, C. Scherer, M. East &amp;amp; S. Kramer-Schadt (accepted) ‘Keeping the kids at home’ can limit the persistence of contagious pathogens in social animals. Journal of Animal Ecology.
  V.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://cedricscherer.com/top/projects/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cedricscherer.com/top/projects/</guid>
      <description>Overview of Research Project As a computational scientist, I apply analytic and mechanistic modeling approaches to answer questions related to the movement ecology of animals and the dynamics of populations, communities and diseases in space and time. By using empirical and simulated data, I investigate how disease dynamics are influenced by movement behavior, landscape structure and seasonality, how disturbances affect stability measures of ecological communities, and how birds respond to global change.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
