<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Tops on Cédric Scherer</title>
    <link>https://cedricscherer.com/top/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Tops on Cédric Scherer</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    
	<atom:link href="https://cedricscherer.com/top/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://cedricscherer.com/top/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cedricscherer.com/top/about/</guid>
      <description>About Me I am a computational ecologist by training and a data visualization designer by heart with more than 9 years of hypothesis-driven research experience and strong skills in data wrangling, statistical analysis, model development and data visualization.
I am working as a scientific researcher (PostDoc) in the Department &amp;ldquo;Ecological Dynamics&amp;rdquo; at the Leibniz Institute for Zoo and Wildlife Research (IZW) in Berlin, Germany. Since the beginning of 2002 I have also been working successfully as a self-employed designer, consultant and workshop instructor in the fields of data visualization and reproducible analysis.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://cedricscherer.com/top/conduct/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cedricscherer.com/top/conduct/</guid>
      <description>Code of Conduct I take responsibility for my own words and all the content created by myself. I am committed to the “Civility Enforced” standard: I will not post unacceptable content, and I will delete any references or comments that contain it.
I define unacceptable content as anything included or linked to that:
is being used to abuse, harass, stalk, or threaten othersis libelous, knowingly false, ad-hominem, or misrepresents another personinfringes upon a copyright or trademarkviolates an obligation of confidentialityviolates the privacy of othersI define and determine what is “unacceptable content” on a case-by-case basis, and my definitions are not limited to this list.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://cedricscherer.com/top/dataviz/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cedricscherer.com/top/dataviz/</guid>
      <description>A selection of data visualizations have produced for personal projects and as challenge contributions using the {ggplot2} package in the programming language R. All visualizations are the result of the code without any post-processing.
 #TidyTuesday Contributions #30DayMapChallenge Contributions #MakeoverMonday Contributions #SWDchallenge Contributions RStudio Table Contest 2020   You need a visualization? Let&amp;rsquo;s get in touch! Contributions to #TidyTuesday #TidyTuesday is a weekly data project aimed at the R ecosystem and the {tidyverse} package bundle to wrangle, explore and visualize the data set that is provided by the R4DS Online Learning Community.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://cedricscherer.com/top/impressum/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cedricscherer.com/top/impressum/</guid>
      <description>Impressum Angaben gemäß § 5 TMG C&amp;eacute;dric Scherer
Birkenstra&amp;szlig;e 18
10559 Berlin
Kontakt Telefon: +49 (0) 176 708 789 84
E-Mail: info@data-vizard.de
Verantwortlich für den Inhalt nach § 55 Abs. 2 RStV C&amp;eacute;dric Scherer
Birkenstra&amp;szlig;e 18
10559 Berlin
EU-Streitschlichtung Die Europ&amp;auml;ische Kommission stellt eine Plattform zur Online-Streitbeilegung (OS) bereit: https://ec.europa.eu/consumers/odr. Unsere E-Mail-Adresse finden Sie oben im Impressum.
Verbraucher­streit­beilegung/Universal­schlichtungs­stelle Wir sind nicht bereit oder verpflichtet, an Streitbeilegungsverfahren vor einer Verbraucherschlichtungsstelle teilzunehmen.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://cedricscherer.com/top/links/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cedricscherer.com/top/links/</guid>
      <description>Content  Rstats  {tidyverse} {ggplot2} Spatial Data   DataViz  Colors Chart Types Mapping   Interesting Personal Blogs  Rstats  &amp;ldquo;Cookbook for R&amp;rdquo; — free online book by Winston Chang &amp;ldquo;Technical Foundations of Informatics&amp;rdquo; — free online book by Michael Freeman &amp;amp; Joel Ross &amp;ldquo;Efficient R Programming&amp;rdquo; — free online book by Colin Gillespie &amp;amp; Robin Lovelace &amp;ldquo;YaRrr! The Pirate&amp;rsquo;s Guide to R&amp;rdquo; — free online book by Nathaniel Phillips R Graph Gallery Five Simple Tipps to Improve Your R Code  {tidyverse}  &amp;ldquo;R for Data Science&amp;rdquo; — free online book by Hadley Wickham &amp;amp; Garrett Grolemund  {ggplot2}  Source code of the book &amp;ldquo;Fundamentals of Data Visualization&amp;rdquo; Top 50 ggplot visualizations Gallery of ggplot2 extensions Extending ggplot2  Spatial Data  &amp;ldquo;Geocomputation with R&amp;rdquo; — free online book by Robin Lovelace, Jakub Nowosad &amp;amp; Jannes Muenchow  DataViz  &amp;ldquo;Data Visualization&amp;rdquo; — free online book by Kieran Healy &amp;ldquo;Fundamentals of Data Visualization&amp;rdquo; — free online book by Claus Wilke &amp;ldquo;Visualizing Data&amp;rdquo; — homepage by Andy Kirk &amp;ldquo;Visual Cinnamon&amp;rdquo; — homepage by Nadieh Bremer Explorable Explanations &amp;ldquo;Nightingale&amp;rdquo; — blog by the Data Visualization Society on Medium &amp;ldquo;Multiple Views: Visualization Research Explained&amp;rdquo; — DataViz blog on Medium Graphics Principles Cheatsheet  Colors  Viz Palette — colors in action (plus colorblind check) Color Space — color palette generator Chroma.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://cedricscherer.com/top/projects/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cedricscherer.com/top/projects/</guid>
      <description>Project Overview  BioMove NLMR (Neutral Landscape Models in R) Multidimensionality of Stability AFT (Animal Functional Type Approach) #TidyTuesday  BioMove The DFG funded Research Training Group &amp;lsquo;Integrating Biodiversity Research with Movement Ecology in dynamic agricultural landscapes (BioMove)&#39; aims to:
  link innovative individual research projects that overcome the apparent gap between movement ecology and biodiversity research, employing a joint conceptual framework;
  strategically combine empirical, experimental and modelling approaches based in one common study area (AgroScapeLab-Quillow, Brandenburg, Germany) of sufficient size to address questions of varying spatial scales;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://cedricscherer.com/top/pubs/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cedricscherer.com/top/pubs/</guid>
      <description>Publications | Invited Talks | Conference Contributions | R Packages
You can also find me on Google Scholar and ResearchGate.
My ORCID ID is 0000-0003-0465-2543.
Peer-Reviewed Publications Accepted  V. Radchuk, S. Kramer-Schadt, U. Berger, C. Scherer, P. Backmann, V. Grimm &amp;amp; S. Kramer-Schadt (accepted) Individual-based models. Chapter for the upcoming book „Demographic Methods across the Tree of Life” by R. Salguero-Gómez &amp;amp; M. Gamelon.  2020   C. Scherer, V.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>