<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Cédric Scherer</title>
    <link>/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Cédric Scherer</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 06 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Hello, TidyTuesday!</title>
      <link>/2019/05/06/tidytuesday_intro/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/05/06/tidytuesday_intro/</guid>
      <description>During my after-thesis-vacation, I managed to tick off two long-term todo&amp;rsquo;s on my list - set up a homepage and to participate in the #TidyTuesday challenge to strengthen my data science and visualization skills and share my work and code tricks with the amazing Rstats community on Twitter. The #TidyTuesday challenge is a excellent opprtunity to do so!
What is it about? The R4DS (&amp;rdquo;R for Data Science&amp;rdquo;) online learning community founded by Jesse Maegan is a great opportunity to train skills related to data wrangling and visualization and forms a network of mentors and learners.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hello, World!</title>
      <link>/2019/05/04/welcome/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/05/04/welcome/</guid>
      <description>Hi, I am glad you found your way here! Come in, have a look.
I finally managed to set up a personal homepage - and how easy it was! Huge thanks to the developers of the R package blogdown Yihui Xie, Amber Thomas and Alison Presmanes Hill and the open-source Hugo framework. Much thanks also to Huabing Zhao for sharing his &amp;ldquo;Clean White&amp;rdquo; theme!
Header image &amp;copy; Negative Space</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/search/placeholder/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/search/placeholder/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/top/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/top/about/</guid>
      <description>About Me | Contact | Curriculum Vitae
About Me I am a computational ecologist by training and a data visualization designer by heart. I use statistical and simulation models to answer questions related to the movement ecology of animals and the dynamics of populations, communities and diseases in space and time. Data visualizations are mostly done in R using the package ggplot2 from the amazing tidyverse which I use for all kinds of data preparation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/top/dataviz/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/top/dataviz/</guid>
      <description>A collection of data visualizations I&amp;rsquo;ve produced for scientific publications and fun using the ggplot2 package in the programming language R. Almost all visualizations are the result of the code without any post-processing. Click on an image to enlarge it.
If you have some data and would like to get it visualized, don&amp;rsquo;t hesitate to contact me!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/top/links/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/top/links/</guid>
      <description> Rstats | DataViz
Coming soon!
Rstats {tidyverse} {ggplot2} DataViz </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/top/projects/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/top/projects/</guid>
      <description>Poject Overview  BioMove NLMR (Neutral Landscape Models in R) Multidimensionality of Stability AFT (Animal Functional Type Approach) #TidyTuesday  BioMove The DFG funded Research Training Group &amp;lsquo;Integrating Biodiversity Research with Movement Ecology in dynamic agricultural landscapes (BioMove)&amp;rsquo; aims to:
 link innovative individual research projects that overcome the apparent gap between movement ecology and biodiversity research, employing a joint conceptual framework;
 strategically combine empirical, experimental and modelling approaches based in one common study area (AgroScapeLab-Quillow, Brandenburg, Germany) of sufficient size to address questions of varying spatial scales;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/top/pubs/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/top/pubs/</guid>
      <description>Peer-Reviewed Publications | Conference Contributions | R packages
You can also find me on Google Scholar and ResearchGate.
My ORCID ID is 0000-0003-0465-2543.
Peer-Reviewed Publications  V. Radchuk, F. De Laender, J. Sarmento Cabral, I Boulangeat, M. Crawford, F. Bohn, J. De Raedt, C. Scherer, J.-C. Svenning, K. Thonicke, F. Schurr, V. Grimm &amp;amp; S. Kramer-Schadt (2019) The dimensionality of stability depends on disturbance type. Ecology Letters 22:647–684.
 M.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>