<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Cédric Scherer</title>
    <link>/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Cédric Scherer</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 05 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>A Quick How-to on Labelling Bar Graphs in ggplot2</title>
      <link>/2021/07/05/a-quick-how-to-on-labelling-bar-graphs-in-ggplot2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/07/05/a-quick-how-to-on-labelling-bar-graphs-in-ggplot2/</guid>
      <description>Table of ContentIntroductionData Preparation with the tidyverseData Visualization with ggplot2How to Calculate the Percentage ValuesHow to Position the Percentage Labels Inside the BarsHow to Color the Bars Using Different ColorsPolish Your PlotAlternatives Improving the AccessibilityIntroductionBar charts are likely the most common chart type out there and come in several varieties. Most notably, direct labels can increase accessibility of a bar graph and reduce the “chart junk” since grid lines, axis labels, and even axis titles become obsolete.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Visualizing Distributions with Raincloud Plots (and How to Create Them with ggplot2)</title>
      <link>/2021/06/06/visualizing-distributions-with-raincloud-plots-and-how-to-create-them-with-ggplot2/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 06 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/06/06/visualizing-distributions-with-raincloud-plots-and-how-to-create-them-with-ggplot2/</guid>
      <description>Table of ContentIntroductionAim of this Tutorial 🏁Boxplots: The Reviewer’s DreamWe Can Do Better: Add Raw DataViolin Plots: The Reviewer’s Nighmare?Raincloud Plots: A Great AlternativeLet Your Plot ShineIntroductionA few weeks ago, I came across this tweet:
Twitter friends - I love violin plots but a reviewer is concerned that “their novelty might distract from the message”. Are there better alternatives, or ways to clarify/address this?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My Contributions to the First 30DayChartChallenge</title>
      <link>/2021/05/09/contributions-30daychartchallenge-2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/05/09/contributions-30daychartchallenge-2021/</guid>
      <description>What&amp;rsquo;s the #30DayChartChallenge? The #30DayChartChallenge is a data visualization challenge with the aim to create a data visualization on a certain topic for each day of April. Anyone is welcome to contribute, no matter which data source or tool is used to create the visualizations. The challenge is inspired by the #30DayMapChallenge which was initiated by Topi Tjukanov in 2019. I did participate back then and while it was exhausting</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My Personal Data Visualization Year 2020</title>
      <link>/2021/01/01/review-2020-personal-dataviz-highlights/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/01/01/review-2020-personal-dataviz-highlights/</guid>
      <description>Uff, what a year! 366 days ago, most people did not expect 2020 to be that exhausting, emotionally and physically (and let&amp;rsquo;s hope for a better 2021—happy new year to you!). COVID19 was literally everywhere, whether in the media or affecting your personal life, and made it hard to focus and keep social contacts. Plus all the other things that were happening: starting off with the bushfires in Australia, the massive series of police brutality protests after the shocking death of George Floyd, tiring and everlasting Brexit negotiations, Trump&amp;rsquo;s madness reaching new levels, and all the news and uncertainty around COVID19 mutations circulating at the end of 2020.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What do I binge next? A detailed overview of the top 250 TV shows</title>
      <link>/2020/11/01/imdb-top-250-series-table-contest-rstudio/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/11/01/imdb-top-250-series-table-contest-rstudio/</guid>
      <description>Update December 24th 2020: My table made it into the &amp;ldquo;Honourable Mentions&amp;rdquo; section. Congrats to the winner Niels van der Velden and all the others that are mentioned!
In consequence, I decided to visualize the top 250 TV shows according to IMDb users as a more helpful table then the original one on IMDb as my contribution to the ongoing RStudio table contest:
 Tables are a fantastic way to communicate lists of quantitative and qualitative information.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Worst Days of the Coronavirus Pandemic So Far</title>
      <link>/2020/03/31/corona-COVID-19-death-tolls-worst-day-so-far/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/03/31/corona-COVID-19-death-tolls-worst-day-so-far/</guid>
      <description>p.small {line-height: 1.15;font-size:80%}Coronavirus SARS-CoV-2, COVID-19 or simply Corona—what started as an epidemic in China’s Hubei province has become a global pandemic, leading to hundreds of thousands of infections and thousands of deaths so far, national lockdowns and quarantines of cities, #stayhome and #flattenthecurve hashtags—and obviously a global shortage of toilet paper.
When the corona pandemic started, I felt scared, curious and tired at the same time.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Comparing the Extent of the Australian Bushfires 2019/20</title>
      <link>/2020/01/09/australian-bushfires-comparison-europe-world/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/01/09/australian-bushfires-comparison-europe-world/</guid>
      <description>Header image by Michael Barth via Unsplash
During a series of massive bushfires across Australia, large areas have been burned and the fires are still burning. The bushfire is one of the worst wildfires globally seen in decades. Although Australia always experiences a fire season during the summer, this time it has been worse than usually: 27 people died and more than 2,000 homes have been destroyed or damaged alone in the worst-hit state of New South Wales.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Best TidyTuesday 2019</title>
      <link>/2019/12/30/best-tidytuesday-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/12/30/best-tidytuesday-2019/</guid>
      <description>At the end of an exiting second #TidyTuesday year, Jon Harmon, host of the TidyTuesday Podcast, asked on Twitter:
What was your favorite #TidyTuesday dataset of 2019? What were some of your favorite visualizations? Why? Let me know with an @ or via #BestTidyTuesday2019!
&amp;mdash; TidyTuesday Podcast (@tidypod) December 12, 2019 I took this opportunity to recap the last year of contributions to the #TidyTuesday challenge. Immediately, several contributions came to my mind and I tried to pick the best from those I&amp;rsquo;ve seen and which I remember.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Merry (White?) Christmas!</title>
      <link>/2019/12/24/merry-white-christmas-Berlin-snow-history/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/12/24/merry-white-christmas-Berlin-snow-history/</guid>
      <description>During this time of the year, lunch conversations often focus around the question &amp;ldquo;Will there be snow on Christmas Eve here in Berlin/Germany?&amp;rdquo;. I remember white Christmas to be a thing when I was a child but in my memory this happened way more often back then than nowadays. And this seems to be in line with the stories of my Berlin-based colleagues about lots of snow during their childhood. But is it true?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My Contributions to the First 30DayMapChallenge</title>
      <link>/2019/12/15/contributions-first-30daymapchallenge-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/12/15/contributions-first-30daymapchallenge-2019/</guid>
      <description>What&amp;rsquo;s the #30DayMapChallenge? The #30DayMapChallenge which was initiated by Topi Tjukanov in 2019. The goal is to create a map each day of November with a broad topic provided by Topi, no matter which tool, and to share it with the hashtag &amp;ldquo;#30DayMapChallenge&amp;rdquo; on Twitter.
 The idea is to create (and publish) maps based on different themes on each day of the month using the hashtag #30DayMapChallenge, You can prepare the maps beforehand, but the main idea is to publish maps from specific topics on specific days listed below.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Visualizing Temperatures in Berlin with Bar Chart Races</title>
      <link>/2019/09/17/bar-chart-race-temperatures-berlin/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/09/17/bar-chart-race-temperatures-berlin/</guid>
      <description>Sunday Two days ago, I was sitting in the sun with a friend working in UX and Graphic Design, chatting about DataViz:
 She: &amp;ldquo;Oh man, last week we had one customer asking for a bar chart race. Do you know these?&amp;rdquo;
Me: &amp;ldquo;Yes&amp;hellip; They are literally EVERYWHERE 1&amp;rdquo;.She: &amp;ldquo;Yeah, and we had some tough time to make that work and to customize it in Adobe Animate.&amp;rdquo;
Me: &amp;ldquo;&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo;
She: &amp;ldquo;&amp;hellip; and I wondered if you could have done this in R?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Workshop Announcements 2019/20</title>
      <link>/2019/09/04/workshop-announcement-datascience-dataviz-tidyverse/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/09/04/workshop-announcement-datascience-dataviz-tidyverse/</guid>
      <description>I am proud to announce three workshops that I am going to lead/teach in autumn 2019 and spring 2020! 🎉 Thanks to all of you for that opportunity!
→ Data Visualization Workshop in Berlin, Germany (Sep 26th 2019)
→ Data Exploration in R with tidyverse in Modica, Italy (Nov 4th to 8th 2019)
→ Data Visualization in R with ggplot2 in Berlin, Germany (Mar 2nd to 6th 2020)
&amp;ldquo;Data Visualization&amp;rdquo; Workshop in Berlin (September 2019) I am delighted to be one of the invited workshop host during the 2-day PhD symposium (September 26th and 27th 2019) at my home affiliation IZW (Leibniz Institute for Zoo and Wildlife Research).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A ggplot2 Tutorial for Beautiful Plotting in R</title>
      <link>/2019/08/05/a-ggplot2-tutorial-for-beautiful-plotting-in-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/08/05/a-ggplot2-tutorial-for-beautiful-plotting-in-r/</guid>
      <description>Last update: 2021-02-09
Introductory WordsI don’t care, just show me the content!
Back in 2016, I had to prepare my PhD introductory talk and I started using {ggplot2} to visualize my data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Evolution of a ggplot (Ep. 1)</title>
      <link>/2019/05/17/the-evolution-of-a-ggplot-ep.-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/05/17/the-evolution-of-a-ggplot-ep.-1/</guid>
      <description>🏁 Aim of this Tutorial🗃️ Data Preparation🌱 The Default Boxplot🔀 ️Sort Your Data!💎 Let Your Plot Shine—Get Rid of the Default Settings📊 The Choice of the Chart Type💯 More Geoms, More Fun, More Info!💬 Add Text Boxes to Let The Plot Speak for Itself🗺️ Bonus: Add a Tile Map as Legend🎄 The Final Evolved Visualization💻 Complete Code for Final Plot📝 Post Scriptum: Mean versus Median🏁 Aim of this TutorialIn this series of blog posts, I aim to show you how to turn a default ggplot into a plot that visualizes information in an appealing and easily understandable way.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hello, TidyTuesday!</title>
      <link>/2019/05/06/tidytuesday_intro/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/05/06/tidytuesday_intro/</guid>
      <description>During my after-thesis-vacation, I managed to tick off two long-term todo&amp;rsquo;s on my list - set up a homepage and to participate in the #TidyTuesday challenge to strengthen my data science and visualization skills and share my work and code tricks with the amazing Rstats community on Twitter. The #TidyTuesday challenge is a excellent opportunity to do so!
What is it about? The R4DS (&amp;ldquo;R for Data Science&amp;rdquo;) online learning community founded by Jesse Maegan is a great opportunity to train skills related to data wrangling and visualization and forms a network of mentors and learners.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hello, World!</title>
      <link>/2019/05/04/welcome/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/05/04/welcome/</guid>
      <description>Header image by Negative Space
Hi, I am glad you found your way here! Come in, have a look.
I finally managed to set up a personal homepage - and how easy it was! Huge thanks to the developers of the R package {blogdown} Yihui Xie, Amber Thomas and Alison Presmanes Hill and the open-source Hugo framework. Much thanks also to Huabing Zhao for sharing his &amp;ldquo;CleanWhite&amp;rdquo; theme!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/search/placeholder/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/search/placeholder/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/top/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/top/about/</guid>
      <description>About Me li:not(:last-child) {margin-bottom: 3px;}I am a computational ecologist by training and a data visualization designer by heart with more than 11 years of hypothesis-driven research experience and strong skills in data wrangling, statistical analysis, model development, and data visualization.
Data Visualization I have been working as an independent data visualization specialist since the beginning of 2020. Since then I have worked for a large number of clients as a designer, consultant, analyst, and workshop instructor in the field of data visualization and reproducible analysis.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/top/challenges/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/top/challenges/</guid>
      <description>Overview of Data Visualization Challenges Content  #TidyTuesday #30DayMapChallenge #30DayChartChallenge SWDchallenge #MakeoverMonday RStudio Table Contest BES MoveMap Competition CorrelAid X Challenge  #TidyTuesday The R4DS (&amp;ldquo;R for Data Science&amp;rdquo;) online learning community founded by Jesse Maegan is a great opportunity to train skills related to data wrangling and visualization and forms a network of mentors and learners. One of the first projects born out of this collaboration is #TidyTuesday, a weekly social data project founded by Thomas Mock that focusses on understanding how to summarize and arrange data to make meaningful charts with {ggplot2}, {tidyr}, {dplyr} and other tools in the tidyverse ecosystem.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/top/conduct/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/top/conduct/</guid>
      <description>Code of Conduct I take responsibility for my own words and all the content created by myself. I am committed to the “Civility Enforced” standard: I will not post unacceptable content, and I will delete any references or comments that contain it.
I define unacceptable content as anything included or linked to that:
is being used to abuse, harass, stalk, or threaten othersis libelous, knowingly false, ad-hominem, or misrepresents another personinfringes upon a copyright or trademarkviolates an obligation of confidentialityviolates the privacy of othersI define and determine what is “unacceptable content” on a case-by-case basis, and my definitions are not limited to this list.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/top/dataviz/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/top/dataviz/</guid>
      <description>A selection of data visualizations I have produced for personal projects and as challenge contributions using the {ggplot2} package in the programming language R. All visualizations are the result of the code without any post-processing.
 #TidyTuesday Contributions #30DayMapChallenge Contributions #MakeoverMonday Contributions #SWDchallenge Contributions RStudio Table Contest   You need a visualization? Let&amp;rsquo;s get in touch! Contributions to #TidyTuesday #TidyTuesday is a weekly data project aimed at the R ecosystem and the {tidyverse} package bundle to wrangle, explore and visualize the data set that is provided by the R4DS Online Learning Community.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/top/impressum/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/top/impressum/</guid>
      <description>Impressum Angaben gemäß § 5 TMG C&amp;eacute;dric Scherer
Birkenstra&amp;szlig;e 18
10559 Berlin
Kontakt Telefon: +49 (0) 176 708 789 84
E-Mail: info@data-vizard.de
Verantwortlich für den Inhalt nach § 55 Abs. 2 RStV C&amp;eacute;dric Scherer
Birkenstra&amp;szlig;e 18
10559 Berlin
EU-Streitschlichtung Die Europ&amp;auml;ische Kommission stellt eine Plattform zur Online-Streitbeilegung (OS) bereit: https://ec.europa.eu/consumers/odr. Unsere E-Mail-Adresse finden Sie oben im Impressum.
Verbraucher­streit­beilegung/Universal­schlichtungs­stelle Wir sind nicht bereit oder verpflichtet, an Streitbeilegungsverfahren vor einer Verbraucherschlichtungsstelle teilzunehmen.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/top/links/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/top/links/</guid>
      <description>Content  DataViz Rstats Interesting Personal Blogs  Rstats  &amp;ldquo;Cookbook for R&amp;rdquo; — free online book by Winston Chang &amp;ldquo;Technical Foundations of Informatics&amp;rdquo; — free online book by Michael Freeman &amp;amp; Joel Ross &amp;ldquo;Efficient R Programming&amp;rdquo; — free online book by Colin Gillespie &amp;amp; Robin Lovelace &amp;ldquo;YaRrr! The Pirate&amp;rsquo;s Guide to R&amp;rdquo; — free online book by Nathaniel Phillips R Graph Gallery Five Simple Tipps to Improve Your R Code  {tidyverse}  &amp;ldquo;R for Data Science&amp;rdquo; — free online book by Hadley Wickham &amp;amp; Garrett Grolemund  {ggplot2}  Source code of the book &amp;ldquo;Fundamentals of Data Visualization&amp;rdquo; Top 50 ggplot visualizations Gallery of ggplot2 extensions Extending ggplot2  Spatial Data  &amp;ldquo;Geocomputation with R&amp;rdquo; — free online book by Robin Lovelace, Jakub Nowosad &amp;amp; Jannes Muenchow  DataViz  Explorable Explanations &amp;ldquo;Nightingale&amp;rdquo; — journal by the Data Visualization Society Our World in Data — &amp;ldquo;data on the world’s largest problems&amp;rdquo; &amp;ldquo;Multiple Views: Visualization Research Explained&amp;rdquo; — DataViz blog on Medium Graphics Principles Cheatsheet  Open-Access Books  &amp;ldquo;Data Visualization&amp;rdquo; by Kieran Healy &amp;ldquo;Fundamentals of Data Visualization&amp;rdquo; by Claus Wilke &amp;ldquo;Hands-On Data Visualization&amp;rdquo; by Jack Dougherty &amp;amp; Ilya Ilyankou  Color Choice  Viz Palette — colors in action (plus colorblind check) Color Space — color palette generator Chroma.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/top/portfolio/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/top/portfolio/</guid>
      <description>Content  Peer-Reviewed Publications Invited Talks Conference Presentations R Packages Media Appearances  Peer-Reviewed Publications You can also find me on Google Scholar and ResearchGate.
My ORCID ID is 0000-0003-0465-2543.
Accepted   L. Marescot, M. Franz, S. Benhaiem, H. Hofer, C. Scherer, M. East &amp;amp; S. Kramer-Schadt (accepted) ‘Keeping the kids at home’ can limit the persistence of contagious pathogens in social animals. Journal of Animal Ecology.
  V.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/top/projects/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/top/projects/</guid>
      <description>Overview of Research Project As a computational scientist, I apply analytic and mechanistic modeling approaches to answer questions related to the movement ecology of animals and the dynamics of populations, communities and diseases in space and time. By using empirical and simulated data, I investigate how disease dynamics are influenced by movement behavior, landscape structure and seasonality, how disturbances affect stability measures of ecological communities, and how birds respond to global change.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
