<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Weather on Cédric Scherer</title>
    <link>https://cedricscherer.com/tags/weather/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Weather on Cédric Scherer</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 09 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cedricscherer.com/tags/weather/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Comparing the Extent of the Australian Bushfires 2019/20</title>
      <link>https://cedricscherer.com/2020/01/09/australian-bushfires-comparison-europe-world/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cedricscherer.com/2020/01/09/australian-bushfires-comparison-europe-world/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p style=&#34;font-size:14px&#34;&gt;Header image by &lt;a href=&#34;https://unsplash.com/photos/OjA6F3pSccw&#34;&gt;Michael Barth via Unsplash&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;During a series of massive bushfires across Australia, large areas have been burned and the fires are still burning. The bushfire is one of the worst wildfires globally seen in decades. Although Australia always experiences a fire season during the summer, this time it has been worse than usually: &lt;a href=&#34;https://edition.cnn.com/2020/01/01/australia/australia-fires-explainer-intl-hnk-scli/index.html&#34;&gt;27 people died and more than 2,000 homes have been destroyed or damaged alone in the worst-hit state of New South Wales&lt;/a&gt;. 800 million animals have been affected since bushfires in NSW have started with an estimate of one billion animals impacted nationally say &lt;a href=&#34;https://sydney.edu.au/news-opinion/news/2020/01/03/a-statement-about-the-480-million-animals-killed-in-nsw-bushfire.html&#34;&gt;ecologists from Sydney University&lt;/a&gt;. Thick smoke is drifting over the Pacific Ocean towards New Zealand and the South American continent. The massive fires have been fuelled by dry organic matter caused by extraordinary high temperatures and a prolonged period of drought which created excellent fire conditions.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;extents-of-burnt-land-and-plume-of-smoke-in-comparison-to-european-countries&#34;&gt;Extents of burnt land and plume of smoke in comparison to European countries&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As of the 6th of January, the estimated area burnt in Australia was &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bbc.com/news/world-australia-50951043&#34;&gt;63,000 square kilometres (~24,000 square miles)&lt;/a&gt;—an area as large as the Latvian country in Europe. The plume of smoke created by the bushfires covered &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.independent.co.uk/news/world/australasia/australia-fires-latest-smoke-forecast-nsw-victoria-food-water-a9266846.html&#34;&gt;an area of 5.5 million square kilometer (2.1 million square miles)&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.businessinsider.de/international/australia-wildfires-space-satellite-pictures-smoke-new-zealand-2020-1/?r=US&amp;amp;IR=T&#34;&gt;can be seen from space&lt;/a&gt;. This area is as large as the area of Denmark including Greenland and the Faroe Islands, France, Spain, Sweden, Norway, Germany, Finland, Poland &amp;amp; Italy together!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cedricscherer.com/img/dataviz-posts/2020_02_AustralianFires_blog.png&#34; alt=&#34;map-burnt-land-smoke-europe&#34; style=&#34;width:100%; object-fit: contain&#34; onclick=&#34;window.open(&#39;https://www.cedricscherer.com/img/tidytuesday/2020_02_AustralianFires_blog.png&#39;, &#39;blank&#39;);&#34;/&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Extent of burnt land and smoke caused by the Australian bushfires in relation to European countries.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;how-much-of-your-countrys-area-would-have-been-burnt-if-the-bushfires-had-raged-there&#34;&gt;How much of your country&amp;rsquo;s area would have been burnt if the bushfires had raged there?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As of 8th of January, the land burnt increased to &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theguardian.com/australia-news/datablog/ng-interactive/2019/dec/07/how-big-are-the-fires-burning-on-the-east-coast-of-australia-interactive-map&#34;&gt;107,000 square kilometres (41,300 square miles)&lt;/a&gt;. To imagine how large the area is, it might be simpler to compare the area to a country you are familiar with:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cedricscherer.com/img/dataviz-posts/2020_02_AustralianFires_Global_blog.png&#34; alt=&#34;map-burnt-land-world&#34; style=&#34;width:100%; object-fit: contain&#34; onclick=&#34;window.open(&#39;https://www.cedricscherer.com/img/tidytuesday/2020_02_AustralianFires_Global_blog.png&#39;, &#39;blank&#39;);&#34;/&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Burnt area in relation to countries worldwide.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;how-to-help-victims-of-australias-fires&#34;&gt;How to help victims of Australia’s fires&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nytimes.com/2020/01/06/world/australia/help-australia-fires.html&#34;&gt;NY Times lists several organizations&lt;/a&gt; that are currently helping to provide support, emergency grants, and housing. You can support them too by donating money or clothing and household goods.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;how-to-create-the-visualizations&#34;&gt;How to create the visualizations?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can find the codes for both maps on my &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/Z3tt/TidyTuesday/blob/master/R/2020_02_AustralianFires.Rmd&#34;&gt;GitHub profile&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Merry (White?) Christmas!</title>
      <link>https://cedricscherer.com/2019/12/24/merry-white-christmas-Berlin-snow-history/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cedricscherer.com/2019/12/24/merry-white-christmas-Berlin-snow-history/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;During this time of the year, lunch conversations often focus around the question &amp;ldquo;Will there be snow on Christmas Eve here in Berlin/Germany?&amp;rdquo;. I remember white Christmas to be a thing when I was a child but in my memory this happened way more often back then than nowadays. And this seems to be in line with the stories of my Berlin-based colleagues about lots of snow during their childhood. But is it true?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cedricscherer.com/img/dataviz-posts/snow-history-fit.png&#34; alt=&#34;white-christmas-dataviz-Berlin&#34; style=&#34;width:100%; object-fit: contain&#34; onclick=&#34;window.open(&#39;https://www.cedricscherer.com/img//snow-history-fit.png&#39;, &#39;blank&#39;);&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a Christmas-inspired visualization of the first day of snow and the total amount of snow that fell in Berlin since the beginning of weather recordings on Germany. The color encodes if there was snow on Christmas Eve (white snowflakes) or not (light blue snowflakes). As one can see, white Christmas was rarely the case but became even more rare recently with the last snow on Christmas happening in 2012. Also, while being quite stable most of the time, the day of first snow tends to be later in December with the trend being after Christmas Eve in the next years. And yes, today there is no snow on sight - it&amp;rsquo;s sunny and temperatures are more like spring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So how about snow cover in general? As we already have seen, the amount of snow varies a lot among years with a slight trend of less total amount of snow in more recent years. While the winter of 1969 was a record year in terms of snow (130 cm snow in total and 101 days with snow cover), the year with the least snow was 2018 - and there also has been no snow this winter either.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cedricscherer.com/img/dataviz-posts/snow-history-clean.png&#34; alt=&#34;snow-cover-dataviz-Berlin&#34; style=&#34;width:100%; object-fit: contain&#34; onclick=&#34;window.open(&#39;https://www.cedricscherer.com/img//snow-history-clean.png&#39;, &#39;blank&#39;);&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am really happy about the overall &lt;em&gt;snowy&lt;/em&gt; theme of the plot! However, it might be a bit difficult to grasp so I also designed a version with some explanatory annotations:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cedricscherer.com/img/dataviz-posts/snow-history.png&#34; alt=&#34;snow-cover-dataviz-Berlin-annotated&#34; style=&#34;width:100%; object-fit: contain&#34; onclick=&#34;window.open(&#39;https://www.cedricscherer.com/img/dataviz-posts/snow-history.png&#39;, &#39;blank&#39;);&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Likely, I will come back to this plot in the next years and, hopefully, I am going to add a white snowflake soon so my daughter can tell her colleagues about snow on Christmas Eve—and also in general—in Berlin and Germany.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I wish all of you a merry Christmas 2019, no matter if it&amp;rsquo;s white, gray or blue! Enjoy your holidays and I hope to see you again in 2020!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Visualizing Temperatures in Berlin with Bar Chart Races</title>
      <link>https://cedricscherer.com/2019/09/17/bar-chart-race-temperatures-berlin/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cedricscherer.com/2019/09/17/bar-chart-race-temperatures-berlin/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p style=&#34;font-size:14px&#34;&gt;Header image by &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.instagram.com/richard.strozynski/?hl=en&#34;&gt;Richard Strozynski&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;sunday&#34;&gt;Sunday&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two days ago, I was sitting in the sun with a friend working in &lt;em&gt;UX and Graphic Design&lt;/em&gt;, chatting about DataViz:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She: &amp;ldquo;Oh man, last week we had one customer asking for a bar chart race. Do you know these?&amp;rdquo;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Me: &amp;ldquo;Yes&amp;hellip; They are literally EVERYWHERE &lt;a href=&#34;#section1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo;.&lt;p id=&#34;back1&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
She: &amp;ldquo;Yeah, and we had some tough time to make that work and to customize it in Adobe Animate.&amp;rdquo;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Me: &amp;ldquo;&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
She: &amp;ldquo;&amp;hellip; and I wondered if you could have done this in R?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, one can! And especially, looping through design choices with a customer regarding colors, fonts, size and also simply to map the relevant data to a bar plot is so much easier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I mean, they have &lt;em&gt;drawn each bar separately&lt;/em&gt; during their progress which took them hours to do!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To demonstrate the capability of R, I immediately sat down after the family went to bed and copied the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/amrrs/animated_bar_charts_in_R&#34;&gt;example provided by Abdul Majed Raja&lt;/a&gt; using the great &lt;a href=&#34;https://gganimate.com/&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;{gganimate}&lt;/code&gt; 📦&lt;/a&gt; (what else?!) by &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.data-imaginist.com/about/&#34;&gt;Thomas Lin Pedersen&lt;/a&gt; (who else?!) to create a smooth and colorful bar chart race with some &lt;em&gt;own&lt;/em&gt; data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am playing around with Berlin weather data from the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dwd.de/DE/leistungen/klimadatendeutschland/klarchivtagmonat.html&#34;&gt;DWD (Deutscher Wetterdienst)&lt;/a&gt; for a few days now—for example &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/CedScherer/status/1170674809983905792&#34;&gt;my contribution to the #SWDchallenge on &amp;ldquo;Visualizing Uncertainty&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;—so this was an easy choice. I created the &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/jburnmurdoch/status/1107552367795412992?lang=en&#34;&gt;usual bar chart race as introduced by John Burn-Murdoch&lt;/a&gt; visualizing the daily maximum temperature in Berlin-Dahlem (one of many stations in Berlin), averaged for each month. 15 to 30 minutes later (okay, add one more hour for playing around with different time periods and frame rates) I was very happy  about this gif:
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cedricscherer.com/img/bar-races/dwd_anim_max_viridis_short.gif&#34; alt=&#34;GIF Chart Race Maximum Temperatures (viridis)&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even though I love the &lt;a href=&#34;https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/viridis/vignettes/intro-to-viridis.html&#34;&gt;viridis color palettes&lt;/a&gt; and they are my default color choice (here: option &lt;code&gt;inferno&lt;/code&gt; because it fits the topic), I gave it another try. The &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/thomasp85/scico&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;{scico}&lt;/code&gt; 📦&lt;/a&gt; is another great color palette package, again maintained by Thomas Lin Pedersen, and there is one particular palette that couldn&amp;rsquo;t match my animation better - it&amp;rsquo;s blue-redish and called &lt;strong&gt;berlin&lt;/strong&gt;!
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cedricscherer.com/img/bar-races/dwd_anim_max_scico_short.gif&#34; alt=&#34;GIF Chart Race Maximum Temperatures (scico)&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was already late and I had to stop. I&amp;rsquo;ve mailed her the animations and while going to bed, I was already thinking about other cool stuff one could use a bar chart race for in this context.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;monday&#34;&gt;Monday&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the morning, on my way to work, I coded an unusual bar chart race (or maybe it doesn&amp;rsquo;t even fit this definition any more?) showing the difference of monthly average temperatures to the 1951–1980 period, and thus both positive and negative values. While showing the general seasonal pattern in the northern hemisphere with summer months being warmer and winter months being colder than average, this illustrates nicely increasing temperatures in more recent years during the summer months and also in spring and autumn:
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cedricscherer.com/img/bar-races/dwd_anim_diff_yrs_short.gif&#34; alt=&#34;GIF Chart Race Difference Temperatures (years)&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I again depicted only the period from 1980 until now since the animation became too long&lt;a href=&#34;#section2&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;p id=&#34;back2&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
To visualize the trend over the whole period (1876–2018), I decided to group the data per decade (to do so in R with &lt;code&gt;{dplyr}&lt;/code&gt; use: &lt;code&gt;mutate(decade = year %/% 10 * 10)&lt;/code&gt;) and visualize the difference in average monthly temperatures:&lt;br&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cedricscherer.com/img/bar-races/dwd_anim_diff_dec.gif&#34; alt=&#34;GIF Chart Race Difference Temperatures (decades)&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, so that the locals can understand it too, I&amp;rsquo;ve created a version in German:
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cedricscherer.com/img/bar-races/dwd_anim_diff_dec_ger.gif&#34; alt=&#34;GIF Chart Race Temperaturunterschiede (Dekaden)&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;tuesday&#34;&gt;Tuesday&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, now I am sitting here watching bar chart races on my laptop in various forms, colors, languages, and time periods.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Me: Wow, it&amp;rsquo;s amazing what you can do with R! And how easy it is.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Also me: Next time, my friend&amp;rsquo;s agency hopefully contacts someone who knows how to use R and data visualization (me!) to make reproducible, publication-ready bar chart races (or any other DataViz)!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id=&#34;back3&#34;&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;Also me: Maybe I should jump on the hype train before it&#39;s gone&lt;a href=&#34;#section3&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and write a blog post.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Footnotes&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p id=&#34;section1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt; see for example: the &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/jburnmurdoch/status/1107552367795412992?lang=en&#34;&gt;already famous bar chart race from John Burn-Murdoch&lt;/a&gt;, the &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/JonTheGeek/status/1172259966260064258&#34;&gt;#TidyTuesday contribution by Jon &#39;The Geek&#39; Harmon&lt;/a&gt;, a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Qvz6xEkSp94&#34;&gt;bar chart race about the popularity of bar chart races on Reddit&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/bizweekgraphics/status/1169232409767886848&#34;&gt;&#34;Bar Chart Race of Bart Chart Races&#34;&lt;/a&gt;.   &lt;a href=&#34;#back1&#34;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Go back&lt;/i&gt; ↑&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id=&#34;section2&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; Here is the long version showing monthly average temperatures for all years (1876–2018):&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cedricscherer.com/img/bar-races/dwd_anim_max_scico_long_fast.gif&#34; alt=&#34;GIF Chart Race Maximum Temperatures (all years)&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;hellip; and differences in monthly temperatures to the 1951-1980 average:
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cedricscherer.com/img/bar-races/dwd_anim_diff_yrs_long.gif&#34; alt=&#34;GIF Chart Race Difference Temperatures (all years)&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#back2&#34;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Go back&lt;/i&gt; ↑&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id=&#34;section3&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt; Probably I am already too late to catch that train... &lt;a href=&#34;#back3&#34;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Go back&lt;/i&gt; ↑&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
