<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>weather on Cédric Scherer</title>
    <link>https://cedricscherer.com/tags/weather/</link>
    <description>Recent content in weather on Cédric Scherer</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 09 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cedricscherer.com/tags/weather/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Comparing the Extent of the Australian Bushfires 2019/20</title>
      <link>https://cedricscherer.com/2020/01/09/australian-bushfires-comparison-europe-world/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cedricscherer.com/2020/01/09/australian-bushfires-comparison-europe-world/</guid>
      <description>Header image by Michael Barth via Unsplash
During a series of massive bushfires across Australia, large areas have been burned and the fires are still burning. The bushfire is one of the worst wildfires globally seen in decades. Although Australia always experiences a fire season during the summer, this time it has been worse than usually: 27 people died and more than 2,000 homes have been destroyed or damaged alone in the worst-hit state of New South Wales.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Merry (White?) Christmas!</title>
      <link>https://cedricscherer.com/2019/12/24/merry-white-christmas-Berlin-snow-history/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cedricscherer.com/2019/12/24/merry-white-christmas-Berlin-snow-history/</guid>
      <description>During this time of the year, lunch conversations often focus around the question &amp;ldquo;Will there be snow on Christmas Eve here in Berlin/Germany?&amp;rdquo;. I remember white Christmas to be a thing when I was a child but in my memory this happened way more often back then than nowadays. And this seems to be in line with the stories of my Berlin-based colleagues about lots of snow during their childhood. But is it true?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Visualizing Temperatures in Berlin with Bar Chart Races</title>
      <link>https://cedricscherer.com/2019/09/17/bar-chart-race-temperatures-berlin/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cedricscherer.com/2019/09/17/bar-chart-race-temperatures-berlin/</guid>
      <description>Sunday Two days ago, I was sitting in the sun with a friend working in UX and Graphic Design, chatting about DataViz:
 She: &amp;ldquo;Oh man, last week we had one customer asking for a bar chart race. Do you know these?&amp;rdquo;
Me: &amp;ldquo;Yes&amp;hellip; They are literally EVERYWHERE 1&amp;rdquo;.She: &amp;ldquo;Yeah, and we had some tough time to make that work and to customize it in Adobe Animate.&amp;rdquo;
Me: &amp;ldquo;&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo;
She: &amp;ldquo;&amp;hellip; and I wondered if you could have done this in R?</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
